Knowing the standard widget library is nice, but as someone who
was once accused as not so much recreating the wheel, as hand
machining my own nuts and bolts, I know there are times
when nothing in the tool chest will quite do the job. That's
when it's time to dive in and build you own custom
view from scratch. Now we're not going to be including any custom
views within Sunshine, but we can still take a look at how
you would build one. We'll start by creating a new class for
our view. Let's call it My View. If
you're building something from scratch, rather than modify an
existing view, it should descend from either view
itself or from surface view. View offers a light
weight, canvas-based approach, while surface view is designed
specifically to support UI elements that require rapid redraws
and/or 3D graphics, using something like Open GL.
It's perfect for views that display video or games.
Now the existing widget library is entirely view
based. So let's take that approach. The base view
class draws an empty borderless 100 by 100 pixel
box. To change that, we override the onMeasure handler,
which allows us to indicate the view size.
We'll also override onDraw, in order to draw our
own custom view content. Now if it turns out
that your view should always be an empty 100
pixel box then you're in luck. Otherwise we need to do
some work. So let's start by setting our view's size. onMeasure is
called when your view's parent is laying out it's children. As
you know, when you add a view to a layout you can
specify a specific height or width, but in most cases you'll
want to either match parent or wrap the content. When a view's on
measure is called by its parent layout, it asks, how much space
will you use? And passes in how much space is available, and
whether the view will be given exactly that much
space, or at most that much space using these parameters.
You can decode those parameters like this. And that'll allow
you to obtain the size and the mode for your
height and width specifications. In this example we're demonstrating just
for the height parameter, but it works the same for
width. We can then use the decoded mode parameter to
find out what size we should set our view to.
If the returned mode is exactly, the view will be placed
into an area of exactly that size. You'll be passed that
value if the layout has specified a specific size or if
the view has been asked to fill the parent. In either case,
it's best practice to simply return the value passed in, unless
that value is below your views minimum size, in which case
you can return the minimum value and rely on the parent
layout to crop or scroll as necessary. Another alternative is AT_MOST. This
indicates that your view can define its own size, up to the
size given. This is typically the case for views set to wrap
content, where the view should be as wide as it needs to
be to display its content, but no wider than that. And of
course all of that's provided that it still fits within the parent
container as indicated by the size
parameter. Now we've just finished calculating
all of that for the height parameter and you'd need to do
exactly the same thing again for width. Once you've done that and
determined the size of your control, you have to call
the setMeasuredDimension method. Here you pass in your width and
height values. If you don't call these setMeasureDimension method, your
app will as soon as your view is laid out.